Long live the king.
Black Panther is a action, adventure, science
fiction film directed by Ryan Coogler.
King T'Challa returns home to the reclusive, technologically advanced
African nation of Wakanda to serve as his country's new leader.
However, T'Challa soon finds that he is challenged for the throne by
factions within his own country as well as without.
Using powers reserved to Wakandan kings, T'Challa assumes the Black Panther mantle to join with ex-girlfriend Nakia, the queen-mother, his princess-kid sister,
members of the Dora Milaje (the Wakandan 'special forces') and an American secret agent, to prevent Wakanda from being dragged into a world war.
T'Challa / Black Panther, played by Chadwick Boseman.
Erik Killmonger, played by Michael B. Jordan.
Nakia, played by Lupita Nyong'o.
Okoye, played by Danai Gurira.
Everett K. Ross, played by Martin Freeman.
W'Kabi, played by Daniel Kaluuya.
Black Panther is a 2018 American superhero film based on the
Marvel Comics character of the same name.
Produced by Marvel Studios and distributed by Walt Disney Studios Motion
Pictures, it is the 18th film in the Marvel Cinematic Universe (MCU).
The film was directed by Ryan Coogler, who co-wrote the screenplay with Joe Robert Cole, and
it stars Chadwick Boseman as T'Challa / Black Panther alongside Michael B.
Jordan, Lupita Nyong'o, Danai Gurira, Martin Freeman, Daniel
Kaluuya, Letitia Wright, Winston Duke, Sterling K.
Brown, Angela Bassett, Forest Whitaker, and Andy Serkis.
In Black Panther, T'Challa is crowned king of Wakanda following his father's death, but he is challenged by
Killmonger (Jordan), who plans to abandon the country's isolationist policies and begin a global revolution.
Wesley Snipes planned to make a Black Panther film in 1992,
but the project did not come to fruition.
In September 2005, Marvel Studios listed a Black Panther film as one of ten films based
on Marvel characters intended to be distributed by Paramount Pictures.
Mark Bailey was hired to write a script in January 2011.
Black Panther was officially announced in October 2014, and Boseman made his first
appearance as the character in Captain America: Civil War (2016).
Cole and Coogler had joined by then, with additional casting in May.
Black Panther was the first Marvel Studios film with a
Black director and a predominantly Black cast.
Principal photography took place from January to April 2017 at EUE/Screen Gems
Studios in the Atlanta metropolitan area, and in Busan, South Korea.
Black Panther premiered at the Dolby Theatre in Los Angeles on January 29, 2018, and was released
theatrically in the United States on February 16, as part of Phase Three of the MCU.
Critics praised its direction, writing, acting (particularly that of Boseman, Jordan, and Wright),
costume design, production values, and soundtrack, but some criticized the visual effects.
Many critics considered the film to be one of the best in the MCU
and it was noted for its cultural significance.
The National Board of Review and the American Film Institute named
Black Panther one of the top-ten films of 2018.
It grossed over $1.3 billion worldwide and broke numerous box office records, becoming the highest-grossing film directed by a Black
filmmaker, the ninth-highest-grossing film at the time of its release, the third-highest-grossing film in the U.S.
and Canada that year, and the second-highest-grossing film of 2018.
Black Panther was nominated for seven awards at the 91st Academy Awards,
winning three, and received numerous other accolades.
It was the first superhero film to receive a Best Picture
nomination, and the first MCU film to win an Academy Award.
A sequel, Black Panther: Wakanda Forever, was released on November 11, 2022, with Wright taking over
as the lead following Boseman's death in 2020, while a third film is in development.
An animated series, Eyes of Wakanda, was released in August 2025 on Disney+.
The film explores themes of africa, superhero, based on
comic, aftercreditsstinger, duringcreditsstinger.
The tone is thought_provoking.